Friends, if the insurance details of your car, bike or any
commercial vehicle are
not updated in the online M Parivahan or RTO records, then you may have to face a lot of trouble.  The
first name among these problems is that of RTO related
services.  That means if you
want to make any changes in your RC like name
transfer or any other changes, then for that it is
necessary to have the insurance details registered in your RTO i.e. M Parivahan records because
insurance is a basic necessity to
fulfill any request and if these
details are not updated on M Parivahan then
it means that you do not have insurance
according to them but if you have
bought insurance and the details are not updated then
we will also learn how to get it updated in today's video.
Another problem could be
that you may get a challan.  Now you already
know this because all the data of M1 and RTO is
connected with the traffic
police or their machines or records.
So if anyone wants to issue you a challan,
they will see that there are no
insurance details attached with your vehicle number,
then they can issue you a challan.
Of course you have a hard copy but if
you are not able to convey them then
legally your insurance
is not registered in the online records and the challan machine
can also issue your challan.  The third problem
that can occur, friends, can be at the
time of insurance renewal.  The
portal of every insurance company is
linked with the data of Aper1.
Whenever you renew your vehicle insurance,
all the data
is fetched from M One records and if the
details of your previous policy are
not recorded there, then you may have to
face a lot of problems in renewal and the
fourth problem that you may face is at the
time of claims.  Now it is not so easy for everyone to get a claim.
In many claims, you have to
go through FIR or court proceedings.  And if in all these
procedures it is found
that your insurance details are
not updated online, then somewhere you may have to
face problem or difficulty in the claim also.
So friends, in today's video I,
Harvinder Singh, will tell you
within how many days of purchasing an insurance policy it should be
updated on Emri One and which
insurance policy details are
updated in Emri One i.e. RTO records.
Like first party, own damage or third
party insurance policy and at the
end of the video I will also tell you that if your
insurance policy details are not updated on error one then
today I will explain three ways to update it.
So let's start the video.  If you
buy any new vehicle like a car, bike
or any commercial vehicle or
renew its insurance in the coming years,
then
your insurance details should be
updated with your vehicle records within 30 days of purchasing the insurance.
What details will be updated on M One or RTO portal?  The
name of your insurance company, your policy
number, and the start
and end dates of your policy.  All these three details should be
updated on your M1 portal.  If
these details are not updated within 30 days,
then how to update them?
We will discuss further in today's video.  Now let us talk
about which policy details are
updated online on M.  Is it
necessary to have a first party policy or
can third party details also be updated?  And if you have purchased an own damage
policy, will its
details also be recorded on M1?  Friends,
as you know that in India, at
least a third party insurance policy
is necessary to drive on Indian roads.  Because the law says
that if someone else gets harmed by your vehicle, then it is
necessary to cover this risk through a third party insurance.
They have no problem whether you get your vehicle insured or not.  That
means there is no compulsion for him.
So the records that are recorded online at Arivon or RTO are of
your third party
insurance policy.  That is, the same
policy number, the same company name and the same
start and end date are entered.  Now
you will say that Sir, I have a first party
insurance policy, so
how will the third party dates be updated in it?
Friends, you know that
third party is also included in the first party.
So the same
start and end date of your first party will be updated.
But if you have only one third
party insurance policy, then I have already
told in the video that if the third party
details are updated then the date of this policy will also be
updated.  And thirdly if
you have an on damage policy.  Suppose
you have bought a new car or a new bike, in which
you get a three-year bundled policy in case of a car
and a five-year
bundled policy in case of a bike.  Out of which the first year is
complete and the next four years is third
party policy.  So, the details of this
third party policy for three and five years will be
recorded in it.  That means the
start and end date of this policy will be
updated online everywhere.  Many times it happens that
when you buy a new bike,
only one year's details are updated in it.  The
records for the next four years are
not shown online on MP One Pay.
What is its reason?  The reason for this is that friends, when
you buy a new bike, its
registration number is not issued there
nor is it recorded in your policy.
That is why only one year's third
party time is updated online.  Once
your bike's registration number is issued,
you need to update that registration number in your 5-year bundle policy
so that
your full
5-year insurance tenure is
updated in the online M1 records as well.  In case of a car, such a problem
usually does not arise because
your registration number is issued to you immediately with the car.
But if your bike policy is
not updated for 5 years then you should get the
bike registration number updated in your 5 year policy.  Along with
that,
your record of all five years will be
updated online on Aery One.  Now
finally friends, we will know that if you have
bought insurance, taken the policy
and its details have not been updated on Ary One, then
how to get it updated.
I will tell you three ways.  The first method is
that from wherever you have purchased the insurance, whether
from an agent, from a showroom
, from wherever you have purchased the policy,
you call them and tell them that
I have purchased this policy number and please get it updated on M31.
Now this is the easiest way.
I am telling this because he
works in insurance.  He has
daily contact with the insurance company.
So they can update your details directly by sending a mail.
This
is a very easy task for them.  If the policy
details are not updated within the first 30 days, then
you just inform them.  Your
details will be updated.  The second method is
that if you have purchased the policy online or are
unable to contact your agent or the
showroom,
then you can directly call the toll free number of the insurance company
and
tell them that this is your policy
number which they will first verify in their records
and then you can tell them
that it is not updated on M.  With just a small
prompt they will raise your request
and your details will be updated on M Parivahan within the next 24 to 48 hours.   The
third way is friends, you
can also directly mail your request to M Parivahan.  The
email ID is visible to you on the screen.
Help Desk Hafan M Parivahan@gov.in
You have to enter this email ID in the address bar.
In the subject you have to write
Update Insurance Details, then your
vehicle number and in the message box
you have to write that I have purchased an insurance policy
for this vehicle number from this company
with this insurance policy number
which is
not updated in my MP One records.
Please update its details in the records
and in this mail you have to attach your RC
and insurance policy
and send this mail.  The
message format of this mail is also
visible to you on the screen.  You
can take a screenshot of it.  You will receive a reply within the first 24 hours
and
your details will be updated on M1 within the next 72 hours.  So
I have told you these three methods.  The first
method is the easiest.  You just have to inform.  To the person
from whom you purchased the policy.  The
second way is to
update the details on the toll free number of the insurance company and the
third way is to
update your details by directly emailing the M1 department.
Now friends, if your
details are not updated on Online MP1 then there is no need
to worry because you have
learned how to get those details updated
on Online MP1.  Generally, what
happens is that when you buy a policy,
these details get automatically updated on the app within 24 hours.
But it is possible that
due to some technical error, your policy details may
not be updated, now you will be able to update it easily.
So friends,
if you liked the information given in the video, you liked it,
you understood it, then
like the video immediately and do not forget to subscribe to the channel
because I, Harvinder Singh, keep
bringing such interesting and informational videos related to insurance for you on the YouTube channel of Insurance Impact.  So please
give permission to me i.e. Harvinder Singh.
I will see you in the next video.  Till then
take care of yourself, stay happy.